Guide to the Omicron Delta Kappa, Rho Circle Chapter (Duke University) records, 1926-1971
Duke University. University Archives
Omicron Delta Kappa, Rho Circle Chapter (Duke University) records 1926-1971
Duke University. University Archives
Omicron Delta Kappa. Rho Circle Chapter (Duke University).
4.25 linear feet Extent: 4250 Items
Contains the records of the Rho Circle chapter of Omicron Delta Kappa, established at Duke University in 1926. Types of materials include bylaws, certificates of membership, correspondence, financial records, history, manuals, membership lists, minutes, newsletters, reports, programs, and photographs. Major topics include governance of a leadership fraternity, member selection, honor societies at Duke University, Duke-Navy relations during World War II, leadership, and Omicron Delta Kappa. Materials are present from 1926 to 1971, however the bulk of materials are from 1926 to 1963.
UA.31.03.0001
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Omicron Delta Kappa, Rho Circle chapter records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974, 1991, 1997.
Historical Note
Omicron Delta Kappa was founded at Washington and Lee University in 1914 as a campus leadership honor society. It soon expanded to other colleges and the Rho Circle chapter was established at Duke University in 1926. Omicron Delta Kappa admitted juniors and seniors as well as faculty members and honorary members both alumni and non-alumni on the basis of character, scholarship, distinguished achievement, and consecration to a great purpose. The five categories of campus life that were emphasized were scholarship, athletics, social and religious activities, publications, and the arts. Election to membership was considered one of the top honors that could be conferred at Duke University. The focus of the Rho Circle chapter was service to the university and community through the cooperation of all campus leaders. The first president of the Rho Circle chapter was Marshall I. Pickens, later head of the Duke Endowment.
The Rho Circle chapter maintained a good relationship with other national officers through correspondence of well-connected faculty and administrators, such as Frank C. Brown. Omicron Delta Kappa became inactive in the late 1960s or early 1970s as a result of general student opposition to the "elitism" of special leadership distinctions. There were also disputes within the national organization about scholarship standards and the fraternity's refusal to admit women. Although correspondence continued between William J. Griffith, the longtime secretary of the Duke University chapter, and the national officers, the society has never been reactivated at Duke.
Collection Overview
These records were produced by Omicron Delta Kappa in the course of their activities as a campus leadership honor society from 1926 to 1971. The bulk of the material consists of correspondence, information on membership elections, minutes, and information on national and provincial conventions. Physical types of materials include by-laws, certificates of membership, correspondence, financial records, history, initiation ritual, manuals, membership lists and cards, membership selection point system, minutes, newsletters, reports both from the Rho Circle and from national and provincial conventions, programs, and photographs.
Subject Headings
Brown, Frank C. (Frank Clyde); Duke University -- Societies, etc.; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc.; Greek letter societies -- North Carolina -- Durham; Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.); Omicron Delta Kappa -- History; World War, 1939-1945 -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Education and the war
Related Material
Photograph Collection
University Archives, Duke University.
Interfraternity Council Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
William J. Griffith III papers
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- General history and establishment, 1926-1962, 7 Folders
  The History and Membership folder contains pages that originally were bound together as a book, dating from 1926-1933. Financial records show the income and expenditures, although some of this information is also contained in the minutes. The folder titled "Point System," which details the system by which students earned recognition by the society, although there is some indication in the minutes that the student body in general was not aware of this system of points. Unclaimed certificates are membership certificates never collected by members for various reasons, and show what the certificates looked like over the years.
  - History and Membership, 1926-1933 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws, 1931, 1962, undated (Box 1)
  - Initiation rituals, undated (Box 1)
  - Point system, 1932, undated (Box 1)
  - Financial records, 1931-1950 (Box 1)
  - Certificates (unclaimed), 1933-1955 (Box 1)
  - Report of the Rho Circle of Omicron Delta Kappa, 1933-1959, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1930-1971, 15 Folders (Box 1)
  Correspondence is divided into three sections: general chapter correspondence, the banquet of 1950, and that of faculty and Rho Circle chapter member Frank C. Brown. The correspondence addresses general chapter business, chapter development, and the initiation banquet of 1950.
  - 1930-1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - 1951-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965-1971, undated (Box 2)
  - Banquet, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Office of Frank C. Brown, 1926-1933 (Box 2)
  - Office of Frank C. Brown, 1934-1939, undated (Box 2)
  - Office of Frank C. Brown, 1934-1939, undated, photographs (Box 2)
- Membership, 1932-1963, 25 Folders (Box 2)
  Contains letters of invitation to membership, responses, and general member lists.
  - Membership elections, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1944-1946 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1947 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1951-1955 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1956-1961 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, 1962-1968 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, honorary, 1932-1934 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, honorary, 1955-1963 (Box 2)
  - Membership elections, honorary recommendations, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Membership lists, 1945-1962, undated (Box 2)
  - Membership updates for "The Circle", 1938 (Box 2)
- Minutes, 1931-1963, 5 Folders (Box 2)
  The minutes detail the interests and activities of members from about 1931 to 1963. The minutes from 1930-1931 are contained in the "History and Membership" folder in Series 1. Some topics covered in the minutes are fraternity rushing, social standards, school spirit, membership elections, national and provincial business, student government activities, honor system and cheating, politics on campus, the Beta Omega Sigma sophomore honor society, Duke-Navy relations during World War II, and campus activities and events. The material related to Duke-Navy student relations is located throughout the 1942-1945 minutes. The January 10, 1942 minutes contain an itemized fraternity plan of wartime economy. The 1942 minutes contain a proposed constitution for an inter-honorary fraternity council.
  - 1931-1938 (Box 2)
  - 1938-1942 (Box 2)
  - 1942-1946 (Box 2)
  - 1946-1955 (Box 2)
  - 1961-1963 (Box 2)
- National and Provincial Conventions, 1930-1961, 5 Folders (Box 2)
  Contains information on conventions such as announcements, programs, and reports are contained in the "National and Provincial Conventions" folders.
  - Notes and minutes, 1950-1954, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes and minutes, 1930-1949 (Box 2)
  - Notes and minutes, 1947, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Invitations and programs, 1930-1961 (Box 2)
  - Convention at Duke University, 1933 (Box 2)
- Printed materials, 1927-1970, 3 Folders (Box 2)
  Contains printed materials produced by the Rho Circle chapter and Omicron Delta Kappa headquarters.
  - Newsletter, "The Circle", 1927-1970 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter of the General Council of Omicron Delta Kappa, 1955-1961, undated (Box 2)
  - Omicron Delta Kappa manuals, 1947, 1968-1970 (Box 2)